Register of the Rena Krasno papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Rena Krasno papers
1911-2008
94036
Hoover Institution Archives
3 manuscript boxes, 1 oversize box, 1 cardfile box, 1 oversize folder (2.2 linear feet)
Memoirs, letters, clippings, reviews, pictorial book, certificates, identification documents, printed matter, photographs, video tapes, and miscellany, relating to the Russian Jewish community in Shanghai during the 1930s and 1940s. Video use copies of selected items also available.
Krasno, Rena, 1923-
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1994.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog Socrates at http://library.stanford.edu/webcat. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in Socrates is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
Russian resident of Shanghai, China.
Scope and Content of Collection
Memoirs, letters, clippings, reviews, pictorial book, certificates, identification documents, printed matter, photographs, video tapes, and miscellany, relating to the Russian Jewish community in Shanghai during the 1930s and 1940s. Video use copies of selected items also available.
Jews--China.; Russians--China.; Shanghai (China); Videotapes.
- Oversize File, 1920-2002
  - Album, Russkie v Shankhaie, by Vladimir Daniilovich Zhiganov, 1936 (Box 1)
  - Certificate for David Rabinovich, Shangahi Ashkenazi Jewish Communal Association, 1949 (Box 1)
  - Diploma, Collège Municipal Français, 1941 (Box 1)
  - Map of Shanghai’s Sephardi community by Joseph Cohn, 1949 (Box 1)
  - Map of Shanghai, Oriental Publishing House, 1946 (Map case)
  - Gabriel Rabinovich file, 1947-2002 (Box 1)
    Scope and Contents Note
    Includes architectural plans by Rabinovich
  - Registration certificate Shanghai, David Rabinovich, 1921 (Box 1)
  - Certificate, Noson Gurman, 1923 (Box 1)
  - Rabinovich family album, 1920 (Box 1)
    Photographs of David and his twin brother Gabriel
- Biographical File, 1935-2006
  - Diplomas and school papers, 1935-1945 (Box-folder 2: 1)
  - Identification cards, 1944-1946 (Box-folder 2: 2)
  - Certificates, 1940-1949 (Box-folder 2: 3)
  - Curriculum vitae, 2006 (Box-folder 2: 4)
- Writings, 1992-2008
  - Introduction to Hoover Institution Archives exhibit, undated (Box-folder 2: 5)
  - "Filming in Shanghai,", undated (Box-folder 2: 6)
  - "The First Inkwell,", undated (Box-folder 2: 7)
  - "Great Powers in Colonial Shanghai: Some Stories You May Never Have Heard,", undated (Box-folder 2: 8)
  - "Polish Refugees in Curacao During World War II,", undated (Box-folder 2: 9)
  - "Shanghai Ashkenazi Jews’ Heroic Efforts to Save European Refugees During World War II,", undated (Box-folder 2: 10)
  - Strangers Always: A Jewish Family in Wartime Shanghai, 1992 (Box-folder 2: 11)
  - Reviews of Strangers Always, 1992-1997 (Box-folder 2: 12)
  - "Mokanshan,", 1994 (Box-folder 2: 13)
  - "Experience of an ‘Old China Hand’ Born in Shanghai,", 1995 May (Box-folder 2: 14)
  - "David Borisovich Rabinovich: A Profile,", 1998 (Box-folder 2: 15)
  - "Leon Ilutovich: A Great Zionist in Shanghai,", 2000 (Box-folder 2: 16)
  - That Last Glorious Summer, 1939: Shanghai-Japan, 2001 (Box-folder 2: 17)
  - Book review, Russian Emigration in China, 2002 (Box-folder 2: 18)
  - "Survival in Shanghai,", 2008 (Box-folder 2: 19)
- Research Materials, 1924-2007
  - Greguras, Fred, "The Fourth Marines in Shanghai, China,", 2007 (Box-folder 2: 20)
  - Shanghai residential addresses, 1939 (Box-folder 2: 21)
  - Dangoor, Renee, "The Jews of Shanghai,", undated (Box-folder 2: 22)
  - Collected articles and clippings on Shanghai Jews, 1924-1997 (Box-folder 2: 23)
  - Clippings on Shanghai, 1947 (Box-folder 2: 24)
  - David Rabinovich materials, 1929-1940 (Box-folder 2: 25)
- Printed Matter, 1934-1997
  - Appeal to Shanghai Jews, Coordinated Committee for United Zionist Action, 1945 October (Box-folder 2: 27)
  - Advertising leaflet, Shanghai, 1944 August (Box-folder 2: 26)
  - Al’manakh ShEK, 1933-1934 (Shankhaiskii Evreiskoi Klub) (Box-folder 3: 1)
  - The Cathay: Magazine and Shoppers’ Guide, 1935 July 16 (Box-folder 3: 2)
  - The Future, Shanghai Jewish Youth Community Center, vol. 1, no. 11, 1947 December (Box-folder 3: 3)
  - Le Journal de Shanghai, 1934 March 25 (Box-folder 3: 4)
  - Leben im Wartesaal: Exil in Shanghai, 1938-1947, Juedisches Museum im Stadtmuseum Berlin, 1997 (Box-folder 3: 5)
  - Nasha zhizn,’, 1946-1949 (Box-folder 3: 6)
    Selected issues: nos. 9, 15-16, 40, 54
  - United Nation poster, 1945 (Box-folder 3: 7)
  - The Young China Pictorial, 1938 April (Box-folder 3: 9)
  - City Guides and Descriptions of Shangahi, undated (Box-folder 3: 10)
  - The Chinese Gold Murders, 1977 (Box-folder 3: 11)
  - Essays on the history of Western-European literature #2, 1912 (Box-folder 3: 12)
  - Essays on the history of Western-European literature #3, 1912 (Box 4: 1)
- Photographs, 1923-2007
  - Family and friends, 1923 (Box-folder 4: 2)
  - Shanghai street scenes, 1923-1940 (Box-folder 4: 3)
  - Class photo, Collège Municipal Français, Shanghai, 1934 - 1938 (Box-folder 4: 4)
  - Purim party, Shanghai Jewish Club, 1937 (Box-folder 4: 5)
  - Hongkou district, Shanghai, 1939-1944 (Box-folder 4: 6)
    Depicts bomb drills and street scenes
  - Rena Krasno with sister and friends, 1940 - 1949 (Box-folder 4: 7)
  - U.S. troops in Shanghai, 1945 (Box-folder 4: 8)
  - Japan, 1959-1961 (Box-folder 4: 9)
    Includes photographs from the Jewish Community Center Tokyo and a visit by Israeli leaders Moshe Dayan, Moshe Sharett, and Emil Najar
  - Rena Krasno in China, 2007 (Box-folder 4: 10)
- Videorecordings, 1995-2005
  Scope and Contents note
  Originals located in Box 5.
  - Holocaust Oral History Project interview of Rena Krasno, 1995 November 20 (Reading room Use Copy)
    Conditions Governing Access note
    Use copy reference number: 94036_v_0005525
    Interview conducted by Sandra Bandayan in San Francisco as part of the Holocaust Oral History Project. Content includes description of the Russian Jewish community in Shanghai during the 1930s and 1940s. "Copyright 1995 Holocaust Oral History Project, San Francisco, CA"
  - Exile Shanghai: A Film by Ulrike Ottinger, undated (Reading room Use Copy)
    Use copy reference number: 94036_v_0005527
  - Rena Krasno's Shanghai Visit, 2001 November (Reading room Use Copy)
    Use copy reference number: 94036_v_0005529
    Home movies of Rena Krasno's 2001 trip to Shanghai: 1. French Concession 2. Tour with Helen and Georgia 3. Lecture
  - KMVT: Croanca interview of Rena Krasno by Fred Marrazzo, 2005 March 10 (Reading room Use Copy)
    Use copy reference number: 94036_v_0005530
    TV interview of Rena Krasno by Fred Marrazzo